Hi everyone, today we're going to learn a different approach. I
write and prepare scripts for voice-overs and similar things. Right now,
most of my work involves creating voice-overs for these tutorial videos or pluralsights or
udemy and similar things, but I'll share some lessons I've learned.
Hopefully, these lessons will be helpful if you have to do the same thing, so let's get started! [Music]
Okay, welcome back. My name is Jeff Bat. If you haven't already checked out my
website, keep checking it out! Here you can learn everything about development, you
can see all my previous blog posts on Clear Storyboards tips and tricks, Adobe's
fascination with AR, and tips and tricks for production. All the different blog posts I've published in the last two years are
here. You can also download templates for
Clear Storyboards and the X API. If you're not familiar with any of these tools, you can check out the full
courses: Clear Storyboards from A to Z, 360 Adobe Captivate XAPI Basics,
Camtasia Clear Rice Custom Scorm and HTML5.  The video is now, as I mentioned before, I've done a lot of
narration, mainly for things like pluralsights or udemy and/or different courses, and
some different things to keep in mind when creating a script, as well as
some different tips and tricks I've learned over the years that I want to share with everyone. Every
voice-over artist has their own stuff. I mean, I don't even consider myself a voice-over artist. I've just
done a lot of narration stuff. Everyone has their own process. Everyone has their own preparation. Uh, you
know, you know preparation and making sure they're ready with their voices. So I don't want to
say this is the best way, but it's just how I've learned in voice-over and scripting
, so I just want to make sure it's
clear because I know some people say, "No, you shouldn't do this," "No, you shouldn't
do that." I don't think it's black and white. I think you know some methods
work for people, some methods don't work for people, it depends on what works for you, so please
keep that in mind. So I'm going to move on and pull out my slides here.
There are a few things to keep in mind in scripting and preparation. This is the first question I get: Should you write a script
? Should you write a script for the video of my blog post? I don't write scripts. I actually
just have a few points to keep in mind.  I came up with a topic, and I wrote down a few
points I wanted to cover. Then I started writing about how much I've done in the last two years, how much I've done this kind of
blog post, to the point that it's easier for me not to write scripts. I'm just being honest, I'm not a
writer. I'm more of a developer than anyone else, but I'm not a writer, and I have a hard time
sitting down and writing exactly what I want to say, and another person. Why
I don't write a lot of scripts is because many times my scripts sound mechanical
unless I write them in a certain way, which I'll talk about here later, but that's one of the
reasons. I don't specifically write scripts for camera videos because I want
them to sound smoother and more dynamic, but that's up to you. So if
scripting works for you, if you feel more comfortable using scripts
, hopefully these tips and tricks will apply to my time writing scripts for pluralsights and udemy,
and other similar things. These tips and tricks helped me get through scripting, so we'll
discuss scripting or not scripting. We're going to discuss scripting using tags.
We'll discuss some other methods I've already mentioned, as well as some tips
and tricks, so first let's talk about one of the key things about no scripting.
No scripting is knowledge, if you know this tool, if you know what you're going to talk about.
It makes things much easier, so that's one of the reasons I can clearly articulate the
storyline and show you how to create tab interactions, just you know to add some key points
, but you don't have to write everything because I've taught and talked a lot about it,
so it flows much more smoothly. The tip for you is to learn your content. If
you're not going to write a script, make sure you know what you're practicing is just for a meeting
or to show knowledge to someone or something similar, or just to pull up your iPhone
and take notes. This can help you practice, this can help you gain knowledge, especially
sharing knowledge and sharing knowledge that others need to know. It really comes with practice; it comes
with you taking it out, doing it, and showing it at different times. Posting
YouTube videos can also help you practice what you're talking about. So here's an example.
I'll quickly extract an untagged script, so I believe this
is a trailer for my pluralsight course and a little bit of stuff they have very specific things to say about pluralsight. They
want you to talk about some things inside, and that's what I'm going to
start using my script here now. If I were to go in and I'm reading this post, then there are a few things that won't really be here talking to me.
This makes it a little difficult for me to read, probably just because of my reading difficulties. It
just makes it harder to hear. Naturally, I'm going to talk about scripting, so
even if I'm not marking it or anything like that, the first piece of advice I'd give is to work
line by line. So that means going into my script and then down and breaking it down into
each line that everyone thinks of here, to make sure it's clearly separated. Now I can go in, and if
I'm not on camera, I can go in and practice a few times. Hi everyone, my name is Jeff
Batten, welcome to my JavaScript arrays and collections course. Practice a few times so that once
you've practiced, you can set a record, and then you can just say that line. Now you can delete it in post-editing.
You can delete the spaces between those lines so even if you pause and go to the
next line, you can still delete that space. So it sounds natural. That's one of the benefits.
Recording is that you can eliminate all the errors by writing scripts. Although I do find that I tend not to say "
um" and "uh-huh," so that's one of the benefits of writing scripts. And it's more concise and clearer. So I'm not saying
don't write scripts. There are some obvious benefits to writing scripts. These are some tips and tricks I've learned while working through scripts.
I easily focus on one line at a time,
practice a few times, click to record, and that's another thing you can do.  You
can mark up your script. There are now several different ways to mark up your script. You
can see them on the right. This has actually gotten me used to several
different things visually, so I'm going to call up the same script here. You'll notice here. Hello everyone,
my name is Jeff Bart, welcome. Here you'll see some different tips and tricks.
We'll cover what all of these mean. Different colors are used in certain areas. Italics are used in
certain areas. Orange is used in certain areas. And pauses of two, three, etc. I'll cover all of these,
especially OSTs, and what all of these mean. If you're new to reading narration, even
with all these types of marking, you probably know it takes a little time to get used to it. But once you've done some of these things by visually seeing these markings
, it will trigger the way you need to read certain areas. Let's delve deeper
into what some of these markings mean. So when you use
different colors to emphasize different areas, the first thing is the color. You can talk about these colors in certain ways.
The first is names. What I usually do is mark anyone's name in blue, or
any similar software name in blue, or any similar name. For example, if I'm teaching JavaScript, I'll talk about
JavaScript, and I'll also mark it in blue. Next is questions, because I want to make sure
I have variations in questions when I get to the questions, because sometimes I will...
Reading it, maybe it's just me, but sometimes I don't read it as a question and realize at the end that
it is a question, so I like to mark them in purple. So when I first started reading
this sentence, it was obviously a question. If I go back here, I'll scroll up, and
you'll notice what I did right here. Maybe this also comes from learning Spanish.
I added an inverted question mark at the beginning and then I set it to purple. You don't have to
do this, but that lets me know from the beginning that it's a question, so I can make sure
I've done the right twists and turns or even paused for a second before addressing the question. So
this is one way I mark things: I do blue for names and things that are very important, then I
do purple for questions, and then if I know there will be a
specific type of screen movement, I'll use red for screen movement, especially if I'm doing narration separate from the
actual screen recording. I'll mark the movement in red so I know the
camera I'm talking about, I know the camera is or these screen recordings are moving.
So this is another useful thing: I'm not sure if I have red here. It doesn't look like I
have any red there, so it's just a trailer. They'll be animated later, so
I don't need to actually mark red, but I've done a lot of software tutorials, so if I know...
I want to go to a certain air area in my software, so I'll mark it red and green,
which are my directions. This is something I won't say, but I just want to hint at it,
or just let myself know something again when recording. So if I come here most often, one of the parts
is done by pausing. So when I speak, sometimes I speak very fast, and I know I'm getting
a lot of feedback, like he's speaking too fast. Maybe when I get excited about something,
I just start in different sentences. So when I'm doing narration,
pausing slightly chillax and then continuing helps me too. The next sentence is
here. Hi everyone, my name is Jeff Batten. Welcome to my course JavaScript and Arrays
and Collections. JavaScript Arrays and Collections.
Pausing to edit to make them sound more natural,
but it lets me know that I not only need to pay attention to this, but there are also
one, two, and three points to show, so they are
different parts I don't need to say, but I need to pause and wait for that
point to appear. Now this one is OST. Now I'm going to talk about what OST
means, but this is the text that will appear on the screen, but I won't specify
what the text is because I don't need to read any text on the screen. I know sometimes we tend to
Read all the content, and the text is on the screen so you don't necessarily need to read it,
so let's talk about making arrays more useful and some other advanced methods. I don't need to go into
advanced arrays; they get the idea there, so that's another thing. Those are the
directions that give me. This is what I need to know to know what's going to happen on the screen, but
after doing it a few times, I won't say it anymore. Seeing green triggers automatically.
I won't say it, but I can pause for a second, and I can look at those directions there.
Okay, so let's move on to the next thing. So the next one is orange. Now orange is looking to the future.
We're going to talk about things in the future. We're going to talk about things that are
exciting, or things you know that are exciting. This usually helps me, well, more about reflecting
excitement. This is something you can take advantage of or something like that, so I'm going to
go back here and get into the script, so this is here. We'll cover what you need to
know about this course. Let me know what I need to be excited about, so we'll
cover everything you need to know about this course, so it's been a bit helpful for me.
One point to emphasize here is looking to the future at the end of this course,
so I can emphasize something different again, which is the color
and some other things I mark up my script. What I do visually is what I also use.
Bold text highlights important words, so if I come here you'll notice things like "map," which are important words, "
set up new data collection arrays," etc., so I say those words out loud so I can
emphasize them at the beginning and read them. So, to make some advanced methods of raising more functional,
I just pause for a second, or I emphasize the word array more.
And another thing you can do is work with bolding and resizing, so
when I browse through my script here you'll notice a few words you really know are
larger than the others because I really want to emphasize those words in this context. Hello everyone,
my name is Jeff Bat and welcome to this course on JavaScript arrays and collections. This helps me
emphasize the actual array, and when I read this script, it visually calls the welcome in the script.
I need to emphasize it, so the more I want to emphasize it, the more I actually resize
it. This is another trick, you can see, as I browse here we have some exciting
new methods, you know maybe you don't want to do that. We have some exciting new methods for
dealing with arrays and data collection. Raising and data collection isn't exciting, but it is if
you are new to it, or if you are familiar with it...  JavaScript, so some people might not be familiar with how to do
raisin collection, so that's why I wanted to emphasize the excitement there. So this is another
way to visually present it, and then there's the typewriter text direction or screen movement.
This is related to pauses, and I'll put it in the typewriter text right here.
American typewriter is text, or you can do Lucid Sans typewriters, or I'll find
any typewriter text, so even text is
visually different from other text on the screen, and more about direction and screen movement, so even the red, like
I mentioned before the inversion, the question mark lets me
know at the beginning of the sentence that it's a question, so I can make sure I
've emphasized the question at the beginning, and there's also the highlighter head snappers. There's something called Head Snappers by
Simon Allardyce. He's an author who's been around for a long time (lynda.com). I think he's the
author of pluralsight and has a lot of popular coding courses. He mentioned some
things about head snappers that I really like, so I wanted to make sure I gave him my credit for it.
But head snappers are when you call the learner back to the screen, when you're talking about something on the screen...
When you're working on a project, you want to get their attention back on you because sometimes people
will turn the tutorial off and put it aside. You want to say, you know what
you know will bring them back, or something very important, or
something you want to emphasize, that's what brings them back. I'm not sure if I
have any
head
snaps like this. I want to emphasize going back to the video and paying attention to the
video. If you have the chance to watch any of Simon Allardyce's videos, he does this
very well, so he's a great example of bringing it back, even saying
things like, "You'll recall yourself, or even anticipate different questions,
like what you might be thinking right now, or what you might be questioning, or what you might have a question in
your head for the learner, because
the learner might be thinking that, and you kind of expect what they're thinking, which will bring
them back. It's a head snap, it needs them, you know, look elsewhere, and then bring it back
to the screen and get their attention." So they are also text acronyms. So you
see OST on the screen, which stands for text not said on the screen. So in this case, we have some
text on the screen here. Advanced arrays: this is not said, but it's just a quick way to get a sense of the text on the screen.  The method of moving on the screen
, so if you want to know exactly what's happening on the screen,
you can put them in brackets and then you can trigger on the screen, or you can just
show the action on the screen so I can know exactly what's happening on the screen even if
I'm recording the screen at the same time I can even move my screen or my mouse.
While I'm talking about it, if you want to get used to it this way, like
I mentioned before, a lot of it is just practice. Practice pulling out your iPhone
and recording your screen. Record yourself as you read the narrative and then you know
it will get a lot easier over time. I've been making screen videos for over two years, but I've been
doing these different plural sites and Udemy courses for over 10 years, so it's been a long time,
so I've learned a lot, but I still have a lot to learn myself, so
it's a kind of progress, you can keep improving in a certain area.
Maybe it's not just about the microphone, but maybe there's a better microphone that can help you or
just a better way of preparing or breathing or other similar methods. Now the
last thing I want to talk about is creating lists or steps. This is what I do most often. What I do is if I go into
my Trello. When I'm preparing a video, for example, if I click on that Trello board, these are
Now I want to talk about something different. This is a video from last week, it's an
interactive video within a storyline, so there are some things I just created that trigger hotspots and
show layers to jump back to specific points. These are some things I want to cover in the video
, so while recording the video, I would put some things next to the video. I didn't,
but I would put some things next to it to let me know these different points, so
if I'm recording something but I haven't written a script and I forget to cover point two well, I can bring
it back to point two and I can make sure I've covered it too. So this is my most
common method, but I've been using scripts and other things that have been populated,
so hopefully this helps you, at least if you're thinking about writing scripts, if
you know scripting for storylines or Adobe Captivate or something similar, and you
want to create a script and mark it this way, hopefully this helps you.
You can at least get one or two things out of this. If you like my videos and
want to see more, say lea rningdojo.ninja. You can go to
my blog posts and see all the previous blog posts. You can also download different templates for developing
templates and clear storylines 360 ax API and videos. You can view the complete courses
from A to  Z's content on 360 has a clear storyline.  This video, a basic explanation of Adobe Captivate XAPI by Camtasia,
explains Rise, a custom scorm, and HTML5 video. If you enjoyed it, please continue and go to
my YouTube channel. Make sure you click the like button and subscribe to my channel, then
click the bell notification so you'll receive notifications for all future videos.
These free videos really help my channel and keep me making these videos, these tips and
tricks, and comment below on which ones were helpful to you and which others weren't in
the video. When you have to leave a comment below my YouTube video, you're done.
That's all for today, so see you next time! [Music] Foreign [Music]